on itself it's uh so people are taking
it seriously that's good it's good I say
that but you're the one who has to deal
with the pain and the pressure so yeah
well I'm in a permanent state of being
freaked out so then I woke up this
morning with all these ideas that I
wanted to talk to you about all right
okay so let me pull up the emails that I
sent you
yeah okay so one of the things did you
want to talk for us just to just to get
our idea straight or what maybe I can I
also want to comment on some of the
things you wrote go ahead one of the
things one of the difficult things by
the way are you recording this already
yeah like you know we say after well
then maybe you should then maybe you
should speak first because that way when
I talk about the the kind of the
questions that I have especially in
regards to the cross the cross is really
complicated it's a complicated it's like
it's it's one of its meant to be to be a
mystery and so the way it's presented to
us it it kind of breaks all the
categories in a way and so or it unites
them together you can rather see it that
way and so it's difficult to it's
difficult to talk about the cross
because it's both totally on the inside
you know it's the center of the world
it's the access of the cosmos it's all
those things but it's also you know at
the edge of the world because even in
the story it's brought outside as
crucifixion happens outside of the city
it happens on the Mount of the skull and
also there's a there's a verse in the
songs that says that the just will never
hang on a cross and so I will never hang
on a tree it doesn't say cross but no
the just will never hang on a tree and
so there's a there's an aporia in the
cross which is that Christ is the just
who's hanging on a tree so that's
actually one of the reasons why Jews
have never accepted Christ as the
Messiah because they can't deal with the
absolute like paradox of having you know
the the the perfect man hanging on a
tree and so it's like how does the
but but for a Christian it's really
bringing together that the extremes you
know I talked about that before well I
think that Christ really isn't the top
of the hierarchy but is really the
stretching out of the hierarchy from the
from the top to the bottom yeah yeah
okay so so all right so we'll get to
that all right yeah yeah because I think
that's a that's that's an interesting
way of conceptualizing the potential
solution to this problem yeah okay so
Derrida had this concept of
undecidability right there were these
things that existed on the margins that
didn't fit into a category system yeah
and we've talked about that before and
that seems to me to be very much
associated with the idea that I
developed in maps of meaning of anomaly
mm-hm
yeah and the anomalous is the monster
and the reason the anomalous is the
monster is because there's a very large
number of things that won't fit into any
category system doesn't matter what the
category system is there's the things
inside the category system or the
category and there's the things outside
and there's a multiplicity of the things
outside yes and so the monster image is
an appropriate image to represent that
because that monster is a chimera that's
made up of parts yes exactly
okay and you always have to confront
what stands outside the category system
yeah and it looks to me like we use our
predator detection and defense systems
as the first defense against that the
first reaction against that yeah because
it's it's an archetypal reality that
there are things outside the category
system yeah
but it's actually and I think that in
terms of phenomenology I would say I
don't know maybe you can actually you
couldn't eliminate this in terms of
evolutionary biology because I'm not an
expert in that at all but it seems that
there's both the the predatory aspect
where it's where the the the the monster
the anomaly is seen as something to
defeat but there's also there's also an
aspect which is the desiring aspect yeah
right right well that's the dragon with
with the gold yes or or the siren the
siren no the monster itself like there's
something about
siren and about the the idea of Lilith
for example in Jewish mythology this
notion of like that or the or the the
Incubus you know the idea of the female
demon which lures and brings you out of
yourself and kind of makes you kind of
waste your seed and in a Christian in
like a religious idea where it's as if
there's a there's something about the
outside of the foreign or the which
elicits a desire to move out towards it
I think you kind of talk about that when
you talk about this notion of the snake
that appears let's say about amongst a
group of chimpanzees yeah yeah yeah
that's the fascination of the unknown
and neurobiologically that's associated
with the positive aspect of exploration
yeah so that's yeah so yeah it's a
paradoxical situation because if it's
unknown you want to be afraid of it
because it might eat you but because it
contains new information let's say you
also want to approach it yeah and that's
really I think it's important especially
now in our in like our situation to
understand the desiring aspect could you
because it you can explain a lot of the
strange phenomena that you know that
turn around sexuality in terms of of all
the strange fetishization of sexuality
into into you know sometimes it's
opposite you know like the weird the
weird scatological fetishes that people
have in like the strange like it's as if
there's something about the the outside
or the monstrous or the the discarded
which can also in a certain instance if
people who let themselves go will pull
them into a desire relationship with
that well one of the things you do find
is that sexual release like orgasm is
potentiated by novelty mm-hmm so that's
a good example of that yeah yeah and if
you kind of go down that route it can
lead you into there's no limit kind of
to where it can lead you and and and it
can explain I think it can also explain
kind of like now we are in this weird
paradoxical situation in terms of
society where since the sixties people
have been telling us you know that in
emphasizing that aspect the idea that
novelty
we'll increase pleasure let's say yeah
bring you further into pleasure but then
realizing that if you go down that road
now we're kind of realizing you know
it's like oh now we're surrounded by
sexual perverts and we're wondering why
we're surrounded by sexual perverts it's
like well maybe you led them down that
road and that road doesn't necessarily
lead to just sunshine and rainbows like
it leads to very dark places which
include a lot of violence and a lot of
of an exploration of animosity and and
and a mixture of desire and hatred and
all those those very strange things that
people kind of let themselves fall into
yeah well you might say that that's in
some sense the story of fucose life yes
exactly
I mean yeah we've talked about that
before that if if you look at foo codes
if you look at fucose life he's almost
like a microcosm of what's happening
today in terms of his he's like radical
exploration of power and sexuality but
also like the idea of the constant
stranger and the constant anonymous
anonymity of sexual encounters I think
that for sure I see him really as a as
someone to look at in terms of
understanding you know the the tone of
what's happening today yeah yeah it
seems to me to be the case and it's
interesting too because Foucault Derrida
didn't care for each other no and you
know Foucault basically regarded Derrida
as a trickster as a word e-excuse me as
a wordy trickster and yeah but they
there are their ideas fall into
alignment with regards to the notion of
the excluded as far as I can tell yeah
well the thing that the difference I
would say with the III find getting that
more useful in terms of you know I've
talked about this in my different talks
about this notion that what's upside
down can be turned back on its head hair
back on its feet and I think that data
is more useful to to play that game
where you can use him and some of his
categories to include them in a larger
frame let's say so that his ideas are
included in a more complete vision of
reality because he has like he really
shows the real his way of thinking
really shows the real deigned the real
problem of post-modernism like that you
know you talk about that off
like how is it that there's this
contradiction for example his philosophy
has been described as like the
philosophy of hesitation you know and
that makes total sense because you know
when you're faced he has this notion
that you're faced you know
and in this slipping and sliding
analysis of the world where all the all
you know reality is multiplies itself is
deferred you know that that things
always point towards the future so you
never know exactly what something is
because it keeps changing and it keeps
it keeps slipping into something else
right and so that actually leads to
which is true things yes exactly and but
that actually leads to this this this
hesitation and if you've ever seen an
interview with the ADA you'll see it in
his in his demeanor he's constantly
hesitating he's hesitating to speak
because he's always kind of like he
doesn't know he realized that he doesn't
know the total implications of what he's
about to say all the time so he's always
like he's he's like he's constantly
cautious and cautious and cautious and
so it seems like that's actually what
should be normally derived out of the
the kind of postmodern idea that that
meaning cannot be contained
whereas Foucault he really he really
used the kind of inverted idea of truth
that you have the truth of the marginal
where you can use marginality as a
weapon to destroy the let's say the the
current order you you think okay so you
think that's more attributable to
Foucault than to Derrida I think so well
did he that does it too but what he does
it's weird because he'll use the
marginal to kind of deconstruct the the
center let's say but then he'll also
kind of in a st. in the same way he'll
also say he'll also heal like reverse it
and then annihilate his reversal so he
end up really in this slippery slope
where you don't even know where you're
standing and and so in my opinion that's
useful because it helps you to see the
the actually kind of in the end it
points back towards logos it points back
towards logos in the sense that we can't
like you like we talked about you can't
live in a world like that okay so that's
so that's that's exactly what I want to
develop today yeah so okay so the first
thing that I thought of today is that
okay so we have this issue of
undecidability from Derrida's the thing
that doesn't fit in the category yeah
okay now and we know that if you have a
category there's way more outside the
category than there is inside the
category because otherwise if the
category isn't very useful right right
and so Derrida talks about that as and I
think Foucault to at least alludes to it
is that that they kind of make the case
that the purpose of the category system
is to exclude and then they make a
political case out of that as well and
the thing is is the purpose of a
category is to exclude it's to exclude
an infinite multitude yeah because you
can't deal with an infinite multitude
and so you have to simplify the world
you have to categorize the world in
order to act on it yeah so then the
ultimate question has to be something
like by what principle do you or what
principle guides your categorization of
the world and that seems to me to point
back to the logos in exactly the way
that you just described because then I
would say the logos is the divine
principle of categorization something
like that oh there are two there are
actually two ways to do it there there's
I think that I talked about it talked
about talked about this in Vancouver
it's like there's either there's three
possibilities there's either the logos
there's either absolute dissemination
which is this kind of the the the idea
that something will just kind of
dissolve it dissolves into uncertainty
and and it's important to understand the
result of that the result of that isn't
that it'll just stay in this kind of
shaky uncertainty the result of that is
that something else from the outside
which has solidity is going to ran
through it and I think that's something
that did he didn't account for you know
for example I don't think they accounted
for
for Islam for example it's like he
thought well if we're all if we all if
we're all kind of in the slippery slide
a situation without firm identities then
we have no reason to fight right that's
kind of like yeah right that's like the
positive infinite number of reasons to
fight yeah maybe
exactly maybe we have an infinite number
at the fight but he didn't see like that
something on the outside which has
strength will this then just come right
through that in terrible actually I am
absolutely well I
he thought he he was probably
Eurocentric in his outlook yeah
hilarious it is it's really hilarious
yeah it's really hilarious okay so
alright so we talked about
undecidability alright sort thing about
undecidability that we need to mention
which makes it more complicated is that
undecidability also has to do with time
and so it has to do and this is
something actually that that you have in
common I think with data which you might
read funny to say but the idea that you
that something let's say you talked
about that in example you said like when
when when Ford created the car yeah
she didn't know what it was because yeah
that that the the the that's a the
totality of what the car represents is
is is manifesting itself in time
manifesting itself in like urban
landscape in the way we understand
economy and in a way it's always the the
like the ramifications were so big that
you could never know what a car is
that's not that's called that's what
Deena talks about in terms of of the the
deferral of meaning in time so there's
that you of difference in terms of um
you know like like that there's
categories in that they're defined by
their opposites and by their their outer
categories but then there's also this
idea of time that makes it more
complicated to yeah well what that means
is that what if they is depends to some
degree on the spatial and temporal
context within which you're interpreting
it yeah you could see that way yeah yeah
I had a dream about that at one point I
I don't know if it's a digression I
don't care I'll tell you anyways so I
dreamt this is such a strange dream I
dreamt that there was this ball floating
above the Atlantic Ocean and it was just
zoom in long about you know six feet
above the surface just cruising along
and it was so powerful that it was
accompanied by four hurricanes one in
each quadrant surrounding the ball it
was a little ball away and that was the
first part of the dream the second part
of the dream was a like a view of
satellites and a bunch of scientists who
were monitoring the hell out of this
thing trying to figure out what it was
the sir
scene was this thing was trapped in a
room it was like in a Victorian Museum
case you know a wood case with glass and
it was sitting up there like suspended
in midair inside the case this a ball
the same ball yeah this so they captured
it and so then it was in the room the
room had no doors or windows and in the
room there was the President of the
United States and Stephen Hawking and so
that and then the room was made out of
titanium dioxide I remember that from
the dream which turns out to be the
stuff that this the hull of the Starship
Enterprise is made out of and something
like that nothing like that yeah yeah it
was something like that and so the idea
was that this intensely powerful thing
had been put inside a category system
right so it was inside a museum display
case and then there was the president
there a sort of representation of social
order and Stephen Hawking he was a
representation of disembodied intellect
uh-huh and then there was the room
itself which had impenetrable walls they
were like six feet thick so we it was
like we got this thing and then then I
was watching it it turned into a
chrysalis
so obviously which is something that can
transform right exactly and then it
turned into a meerschaum pipe it took me
about a year to figure that out it was
an allusion to that famous painting by
Magritte right yeah this is not a pipe
this is not a pipe you know that
Foucault FC like quite a bit yeah yeah
yeah and then it shot out of the room
like there was nothing there interesting
yeah that's a great dream Wow it was a
great dream man and so and it does
allude to this idea that you can't
capture the thing in permanently in a
category system because it shifts and
turns yeah yeah so okay so so fine so
we're on board with that all right so
now the category has to exclude because
reality is so complex that you have to
categorize it because otherwise you're
swamped yes good metaphor for it yeah
and I said something that the postmodern
is that I didn't totally see the the
extent to which that could be all right
right absolutely I think he put I think
he thought that order was a lot more
solid than it was yeah
so so or than it is so then I was
thinking okay so now in with identity
politics you have the politics of the
excluded alright so so then you have
people excluded because of race or
because of gender or because of sexual
identity or whatever and one of the
problems we've seen with that is that
the number of excluded keep multiplying
that's why you get that extension of the
letters in the LGBTQ acronym right and
there doesn't seem to be any limit to
that and the reason for that is there is
no limit to the number or excluded
because it's the cake the category of
excluded is the category of all things
that don't fit in the category system
and that's an infinite set right yeah
okay so but then I woke up this morning
and I thought well we could do we could
calculate that mathematically so because
because of I was thinking about the rise
of intersectionality and then because
the rise of intersectionality is
actually the reoccurrence of the
individual within the collective ideas
of postmodern neo Marxism because you
might say well I'm excluded cuz I'm
black or I'm excluded because I'm a
woman and then someone puts up their
hand and says well those two categories
don't include black woman they don't
include the intersection of the of the
two categories and that there's no
reason that black and woman is more
important than black woman okay so then
I thought all right so that's fine so
the problem is is that you start to get
smaller and smaller numbers of people as
exemplars of the categories that are
excluded and then so then I thought well
how many categories do you need to add
in an intersectional analysis before
you're actually down to one in a billion
because I'm led to you you'd have
fractionated down to the individual
right so now it's kind of screwy
mathematically because it depends on the
gradations of your category system right
I mean I could call you old or young
that'd be binary right but I could say
no no you're on a scale from 0 to 100
mm-hmm so that would that would be that
would give you a point 0 1 probability
of there'd be a hundred groups that you
could belong to in a
so I thought well let's just use a
hundred as an example because it could
be - or it could be ten thousand it's
arbitrary because we could say that
well I'm 41 and and there's advantages
and disadvantages that go along with
that but someone else could say well I'm
41 in six months and there's a slightly
different set of advantages and
disadvantages that go along with that
then so anyways if you have six
categories with a probability of 0.1
then you're one in a billion so you just
need six dimensions of intersectionality
before you've fractionated the
population down to the level of the
individual yeah so so that that means
the individual comes sneaking back into
the collective ideas of post-modernism
once you hit six intersectional
categories as long as that was I thought
that was really well it's ridiculously
amusing so I said this will do the trick
so if you're multiracial woman who's
bisexual 27 years old
smart 30th percentile for attractiveness
10th percentile for familial wealth and
80th percentile for education there's
there is the you're the only one in the
world like that so okay so then I was
thinking okay so now then I was also
thinking about this from a scientific
perspective so the reason you assign if
you're gonna do an experiment on two
groups you know you you do something to
one group and not to the other group but
to make the control group proper you
have to assign randomly to each group
and the reason you do random assignment
infinite number of variables you can't
control for and so you assign randomly
so that infinity cancels it cancels
itself out and the only difference
you're left with is the experimental
condition uh-huh and then but scientists
sometimes try to get around that like we
used to study people who were sons of
alcoholics and multi-and they had a
multi-generational family history of
alcoholism and then we were trying to
figure out what might distinguish them
from a normal person let's say
so we try to get a control group to
contrast them with so we bring them into
the lab say and give them alcohol and
give the control group alcohol but the
problem was we didn't know what to
control for like because alcoholism goes
along with antisocial personality
disorder so do you control for that
uh-huh um do you control for education
do you control for IQ do you control for
socio-economic status like the answer is
you don't know because you don't know
how those are associated with the
alcoholism you can't know and so you
guess and then you do an analysis of
covariance but the problem is is that
you don't know what to covary which is
why you need random assign a shinto
groups it's the only way of solving that
problem uh-huh okay so the same problem
of undecidability in some sense pops up
very very frequently in clinical
research right yeah the same thing
happens if you're trying to figure out
schizophrenia you need a control group
well how about siblings the siblings who
don't have schizophrenia uh-huh well
yeah except they have a different
genotype you know it's an it's an
impossible problem to solve
fundamentally which is why you need
random assign a shinto groups because
you can't control for all the variables
you can't know in advance what's
relevant uh-huh all right so then I had
this so I thought that was very funny
that the idea of individuality comes
back and I never did right with
intersectionality yeah it's it's just
you just push intersectionality to six
dimensions and bang you're down to the
individual huh all right so then I had
this little vision so I'm gonna tell you
the vision okay all right all right so
imagine a pyramid like imagine a plane
first like at a place in a place a land
but flat and then imagine a pyramid yeah
and then around the pyramid some
distance from it is a wall okay so think
about that just as the basic schema of a
walled city yeah okay now the pyramid is
the group that's in there let's say and
the value structure that that group
Orient's itself by okay now outside that
wall there's a very large number of
other pyramids and that's basically the
postmodern world I would say that's kind
of the world that Derrida described and
Foucault set reasonable
hmm III don't yeah I mean could continue
her example I think okay that I think
that for sure that Dida would say would
say something like we talked about the
problem of the contain even the
contained space you know the idea of the
wall and the pyramid like he would he
would have he would have a problem you
would have a problem with that structure
itself like for him that would be that
would be it wouldn't be a solid
structure right no it would have been
flow with Tanya right that's okay we'll
get to that
that's okay fine it's no problem let's
say that is the problem right okay so
you added another dimension to it the
problem is there's an inside in a wall
and an outside that's problem number one
the outside excludes we could call that
problem number two problem number three
is that the center will not hold right
right and that's the same problem as far
as I'm concerned as the serpent in the
Garden of Eden yeah okay okay good good
so so let's say that really is the
problem I mean fundamentally yeah
usually if you go back to the Garden of
Eden you find the problem somehow okay
okay so now now imagine that outside the
outside the wall all those pyramids
fragment and they fragment down to the
level of individual people so they
decompose to the level of individual
people yeah because that's how much
variability there actually is right
because those groups were artificial
constructions right and so you can
fragment them down to the individual
okay so now the question is you want to
let some of those people into the
enclosed okay now next part of the
vision the pyramid grows across on top
of it mm-hmm
now it's a church and it's the center
and the cross represents whatever the
ordering principle of that Center is
uh-huh okay so then I would say and
you're gonna add to this because you did
at the beginning of the talk already the
cross is the center point of the world
it's the axis of the world so it's the
world tree it's also the the place of
suffering and it's the place of
suffering accepted voluntarily and
transcendent
huh it's all of those things yeah okay
and so that that cross is also a symbol
of the hero and the hero is the person
who confronts chaos and gain something
of value from it so that's voluntary and
the hero is also the person who recasts
the archaic structure of the structure
when it's necessary uh-huh right and so
you see those hero themes developed
quite regularly across any reasonable
historical span of time so that's the
Redeemer
that's the messiah right it's that makes
order out of chaos and then huh takes
order when it's too rigid
yeah and breaks it apart and recast yeah
yeah you see that in the story of King
David you see that actually really well
like very very well he he breaks like he
acts as a fool and as a as someone who
is actually a kind of thief trickster
figure while the tyrant is in power and
then when that tyrant fall then he comes
in and creates a new centralized order
by bringing the ark to Jerusalem so he
has that whole arc in his story okay
good version okay okay good I'll keep
that in mind for when I get to that
story in my biblical lectures all right
so now you have to open the door on on
on the wall and the question is who do
you let in so here's the idea okay so
you need to have a center and the center
has to hold because things are too
complex without a center and a category
system and then the question is let's
say that your category system has to
exist in accordance with the process
that creates it and revitalizes it
because otherwise it can't maintain its
to build on across time it degenerates
into chaos or it rigidify zin to too
much order right okay so the only people
that you let into this the inside the
wall are those who agree to live by the
rules ethic and the ethic that's
symbolized by the cross yeah that's two
things that's the willingness to abide
by a certain level of social
organization but it's more importantly
it's also the ability to transcend that
and to participate in the process but by
which chaos is confronted and
voluntarily voluntarily confronted and
reordered and also to participate in the
process by which order is broken when
it's too rigid and brought back that's
the death and resurrection essentially
yeah so those are the only people that
you can let inside the structure without
pose without them posing a fatal threat
to the structure itself and then if the
walls fall then the infinite multitudes
stream in and we're done no I mean we
say it ceases to exist it's like you
just cease to exist that's all you know
that that's all that's all it is right
well you'd also say that that's that's
the problem that's being fought about in
some sense with regards to the border
issue in Europe yeah do we have a right
to have a border right and then I was
thinking today about a store like just
take your typical grocery store and you
say well it's a it's a category system
only those with money are allowed to
bring food out of this place right and
you might say well that's that's a
terrible imposition of capitalist
patriarchy on and an unfair imposition
of capitalist patriarchy so you throw
the doors open and you say everybody
come and take what they want
yeah and that works really well until
the store is empty and then that's the
end of that yeah because if everyone can
do anything they want whenever they want
then not then it's complete and utter
chaos
yeah it's nobody and then what happens
is what happens you know because I've
lived in a place that is absolute and
utter chaos and and cast doesn't cannot
sustain itself so usually what happens
is the rise of a warlord or tyrant the
rise of someone who will by sheer force
by sheer physical force impose their
will on others because the others will
be will have nothing to unite them and
so it's not it's not true that you know
a lot of you know you you meet
anarchists you know and people who think
that that there is such a thing as like
you know there's just kind of free
anarchy where everybody is equal and
everybody you know can do whatever they
want that doesn't
cuz in that Anarchy comes a tyrant
inevitably right there's no there's no
stopping it right into anarchy comes a
tyrant yeah absolutely absolutely and
that's the that's and and then the
problem with that is that the
fundamental organizing principle the
tyrant is tyranny yeah pure QR power
pure power and pure also personality
cult like that it's that it's that
person instead of being an ideal unto
which we we serve you know or our mythic
figure or or a divine figure it becomes
a guy you know it becomes becomes Hitler
or it becomes you know it becomes
Napoleon or it becomes solid or become
whatever like it's the it's that person
everything is embodied in their
personality like I always say like I
always have this image of of a
functional system is is the person who
in some manner is able to to at least
symbolically step down from their power
right they always say that that yeah
George Washington what made him so great
is that he he stopped being president
right created the impetus for the system
to work and in the same in the Roman
Empire like Augustus you know people
will will say that he didn't really do
it but when Augustus became Emperor he
stepped into the city as a citizen and
he gave away all his power and by giving
away all his power in a strange way he
actually became the most powerful person
in Rome but his power was not a legal
power it was like it was like there was
something about his capacity to not be
the tyrant which which would stabilize
the Empire and made him very powerful
but in a in a strain in a very kind of
strange ways different right so so like
a legitimate ruler has to be bound by
proper sovereign Authority exact not if
he gave himself to the to the to the
Senate and said I'm at your service and
so it made him very powerful but he also
kind of bound his power through in the
Senate right right well you see that
emerging as early as Mesopotamia where
Marduk or where the Emperor had to act
out his his embodiment of Marduk in the
new you
festival and Marduk was the God hero who
went out and confronted the dragon of
chaos and made the world and so the
reason that the Emperor had it's not
sovereignty legitimacy the reason they
have never had legitimacy is because he
was acting out an archetypal pattern
that transcended his own personality
then the question is well what's that
archetypal pattern in the answer to that
is that's the hero who recasts that the
tyrannical state and who confronts chaos
so the structure that the answer to the
problem of how you maintain a structure
in the in the flow of time is that you
make the structure itself subordinate to
the principle by which the sir the
structure is generated and then and that
means that the the sovereign needs to be
responsible to the word essentially
that's that's how I would think about it
from a judeo-christian perspective now
and that's above everything yeah and
it's the thing that does the
categorization initially that's when God
creates the world because of the word
and when Adam names the animals and all
of that and then so but also maintains
that across time because it does slip
and slide yeah so you know it did wasn't
really see we've been talking about a
post post-modernism right and about a
logo centrism and we've been kind of
laughing about that too because of
because of its reference to Derrida's
fellow go centrism but it's funny too
you know because if you look at hindu
representations of the center they're
not fellow go centric the fellows is
embodied in its the Lingam and the yoni
now the phallus is conjoined with the
yoni it's a it's a masculine female
duality that's at the center it's not
just the masculine right and so the idea
that that Center is necessarily fel logo
centric is is also wrong right but it
you know the thing is that okay this is
gonna get explicit I guess but but it is
his follow go centric you know that even
if you imagine the the phallus inside
the inside the the woman the woman the
the phallus is the center and
woman envelops the the centre-right the
phallic center you know but I think that
that what I've been trying to get to and
I think what we've all been trying to
get to what you've been trying to get to
to is is to be able to speak of logo
centrism as in the proper manner that is
to understand that to say logo scent
logo centrist means that we also
understand like the the power of the the
out the power of the frame let's say so
the image eyes I have of the logo
centrism is really there's a there's an
image of the mother of God of Mary with
our hands up like this and in her Center
there's a there's there's a circle and
out of her Cudi's coming the Christ
child and inside that that that circle
you see the stars as if it's like the
entire cosmos right which is the frame
for the logos to manifest itself in and
so yeah yeah that in those open virgins
to that 14th century where Mary is
holding a globe I think generally
speaking and then she opens up and
inside you have God the Father and he's
holding Christ on the cross and it's a
it's a it's a similar sort of similar
sort of notion right and so I think that
if we understand it that way there's
like an implicit in the notion of the
law of logos centrism there's an
implicit kind of secret mention of the
power of the feminine in that very term
if we understand it fully as the the the
need for the this kind of the kind of
chaotic outside or the chaotic
potentiality which frames the
manifestation of the logos and and to
understand that those two things need
each other like the you know the logos
doesn't manifest himself without a
question right there has to be a
Christian for there to be an answer and
the question is a frame for the answer
it's like definitely okay that's really
important that's like super important
and it shows how powerful the feminine
is because it actually acts as the the
category they'll I could say the frame
in which the answer is given okay okay
so so let's let's develop that for a min
so um let me let me see that had made me
think of something look I also wanted to
tell to talk to you about oh yes so okay
so you said the frame is determined by
the question that's answered
yeah that's asked yes good good perfect
so so this is where I've been butting
heads with Sam Harris and where you
butted heads with Weinstein in in
Vancouver right okay so because the
question is okay so you have to have a
category system now Harris basically
claims that you can derive the category
system from the from the fact yeah right
but the objection to that is there's an
infinite number of facts and they don't
tell you what to do with them yeah okay
so I would say instead that you derive
the category system from your aims
because categories are there to to help
you fulfill your your goals that's
that's how category systems work
yeah that's why I think of them as
pragmatic yeah okay so now the question
is given that your your category system
includes and excludes and defines the
world what should be the aim of the
category system and so I think that's
what the Sermon on the Mount talks about
because it basically says well you
should aim at the highest possible good
you should aim at union with God
whatever that might mean that you aim at
the highest possible good with fully
right fully right down to the bottom of
your soul if you can manage it so that
you're not broken and bent up and twist
it in a bunch of different sub
personalities so you try to unify
yourself as a force for the highest good
and you do that in large part by
deciding that being is worthwhile right
so you pledge allegiance to to the
concept of being so you're not you don't
like Cain now and then you speak truth
in the service of that being and then
that from that your category system
flows and so that's another reason that
pyramid with the Cross is the center of
the category system yeah because then
you get a category system that includes
what it should include if the goal is
the establishment of the kingdom of God
let's say yeah which is the highest of
possible goals and
excludes what it should exclude yeah one
of the things to that that kind of
differentiates that's a Christian
ontology or like a Chrisman a Christian
cosmology is that we have this idea that
there is an intimate relationship also
between let's say the highest and the
lowest there's a there's something which
which unites them together completely so
that so that so that even beyond let's
say there's this capacity to move
outside how can I say this - to unite
things together and so there's this idea
let's say like you know for example
there's an idea like the idea of a
normal of a Christian family let's say
that you know the father is the head of
the household you know like this idea
that people hate today
but there's this really the sense that
the head or that nor the the king or the
chief exists for the for the the benefit
of those that are glow that are the
lowest right that's continually insisted
upon in the Old Testament yeah because
the prophets always come up and say to
the king you're not attending
sufficiently to the widows and the
orphans yeah and that means that you've
become corrupt yeah so in a way you can
kind of see the hierarchy moving up in
the sense of things looking up towards
you know into the hierarchy but then
there's also a really important man in
which the hierarchy moves down and so
the idea is that the top of the
hierarchy exists for the bottom of the
hierarchy it's like and so that so the
top of the hierarchy and us in a really
important way as a sack is a sacrificial
existence and so the highest thing is is
is there the highest road is the one
that sacrifices itself for those that
are yeah think about that you can think
about that practically as the
willingness of a father to care for an
infant yeah right now so because the
infants obviously the and of course the
infant also has that potential which is
why the infant is made sacred as well in
that in that symbolic realm so the high
is deserving the lowest the lowest is
the infant let's say because it's most
helpless but the infant is also the
future of the hierarchy yeah
and so the I mean I think that that
really in a we've talked about this
before slightly is that the the notion
that the Christian hero you know is
slightly is actually slightly different
from the pagan hero for example so the
night let's say in Western Christianity
the night would be the the archetypal
image of the Christian hero which is the
notion of an aristocrat a warrior you
know a soldier whose purpose is not to
it is not only to gain honor on himself
but in a way he gains honor on himself
by sacrificing himself
for those who can't do it and so he his
honor is based on the fact that he's
willing to fight for the for the widow
for the orphan for those that that don't
have the strength to fight for
themselves and so obviously in reality
that doesn't always play out I mean but
but the ideal is there the ideal is real
and it's it's the basis of all our all
our hero movies all our hero stories
always had this idea of the here is the
person who's willing to use their
strength and their power to the
defense's weak yeah to sacrifice
themselves for the for the weak
which is very different from the pagan
hero like a you know a killer his
weakness weakness was contemptible under
those circumstances is sitting in his
tent and he's moping and whining because
we've taken away his sex slave and he
won't go back to fight until it affects
him personally you know but he he's
actually not he doesn't care that much
about helping you know the Greeks and
their cause he's really doing that doing
things for his own honor and so he's
perfectly heroic and sitting in his tent
and moping and not going back into into
battle you know because his honor has
been attained whereas in Christianity
you know in stories like like if you see
Sir Gawain and uh you you read um the
the the the night and a cart for example
that idea of Lancelot who is willing to
be seen as a criminal as a you know as
the worst kind of person in order to
save the help
damsel-in-distress you know he's he's
willing to sacrifice all his honor in
order to help that that person who is in
danger so it's a really it's a very
different way of seeing the world okay
well I don't know what to say after the
whole thing but it's a the idea of the
cross absolutely I'm not I'm not I'm not
suggesting at all that that was not
relevant to what we've been discussing
it's dead relevant I really like the
idea I know we've talked about the fact
that you know I've been conceptualizing
Christ as the not as the apex of the
hierarchy symbolically speaking but the
apex to such a degree that it actually
detaches itself from the hierarchy sort
of like Horus the bird the the Osprey or
the what the hell is he a falcon in
Egyptian symbolism right he's the thing
that flies above everything that can see
or the Egyptian I and your correction
was that it's not exact once you're
detached in some sense you're not at the
top anymore you're everywhere right
spread throughout the entire structure
which yeah which is a very good way of
looking at it right the story of Christ
is in historian in his symbolism you see
that he's at the top of the dome let's
say in the church where he's really
exactly what you're saying this kind of
did this kind of detached top of the
hierarchy but then he also stretches all
the way down into death into Hades into
de chaos and the cross is the other side
where you know he is he's outside of the
city being being killed by by his
friends by the you know he's the the
outcast he's all of those things and so
he he unites the two extremes of the
hierarchy together and fills the
hierarchy with with well a neat little
idea that he transcends death again I'm
just gonna take this from a
psychological perspective because the
theological waters are getting too deep
for me here well they are because I
don't understand that exactly I'm really
trying to work it out but I don't
understand it well enough yet but the
idea that Christ descends into hell and
rescues people from hell and death that
can be read quite straightforwardly
psychologically because the car
acquaints of not of erecting a category
structure that isn't predicated on the
hero is that everyone will be in hell
and die mm-hmm so I mean that's what
happened in the Soviet Union as far as
I'm concerned and so those health
stories are real enough as far as I'm
concerned but that doesn't speak to
their potential transcendent reality now
as a whole different issue I mean here's
something else that's been that's been
bugging me and I'm just starting to
think this through you don't I do think
that there's there's an idea that if
you're in the right place at the right
time that everything comes together and
loads up you know and I was wondering
you know how the story like the story of
Christ is told in many many ways like
from the cosmic to the microcosmic right
so and one of the macrocosmic stories is
the relationship between the
astrological speculations and Christ
himself and so there are 12
constellations like there are 12
disciples and huh the Sun is Christ
essentially yeah and that story really
works it even Maps onto the calendar
properly right and so then you think
well that's because people have one
interpretation of that is that's because
people have retold the story at each
level of analysis but another possible
reason for that is that it's synchronous
in some sense and then it is the fact
that everything comes together around
that central axis in a in a in a real
way yeah and that the story can't help
but be represented at multiple levels of
reality simultaneously because that's
what the story is that's then that I
mean it's like that's exactly what it's
about the whole the whole thing is about
this this this lining up of everything
you know like of everything yeah
yes okay it's hard to see that it's so
it's hard to see the fullness of that
when you look at it it always kind of
jars you because it's so you know the
story of Christ I always tell people
like if you pay attention to it it'll
constantly be knocking you down because
it it seems even at a first glance
sometimes it seems like it's
contradictory because Christ is all
these things like you know he's he's the
teacher he's the king he's the shepherd
you know he's the outcast he's the he's
he's the
technician you know he's the artist he's
and so it's like how is it that a story
Canon company and the more you look in
the story the way he's a fisherman you
know he's into all these things how did
all these things can fit in one story
it's easy to glance over because it's so
short you read a gospel you kind of go
through it but then if you really look
at all the the aspects and you
understand the traditional categories
let's say that in a normal world the
let's say the the Shepherd and the the
agriculturalists usually are not the
same person but in Christ they're the
same person he's able but he's slower as
he fish exact he's but he's also the
fisherman yeah and he's so he's the
stumbling stone but he's also the
capstone so he stretch it like a we talk
about this idea of stretching out the
entire hierarchy so he's he's like he
he's that's he's the stone that doesn't
fit
so here's yeah right exactly that the
builder rejected yeah okay so one of the
things I've I've come to understand
about tyrannies is that if you have a
terror terror analytical person at the
top the tyranny isn't just at the top
the tyranny is mirrored like the entire
hierarchy right it's like like a what
are those 3d holographs it's like there
are hologram it's like a hologram every
part is a reflection of the whole and so
I wonder if that's analogous if you have
a pyramid
say with the principle of the divine
hero at the top then what happens is
that's reflected at every single level
of the of the hierarchy yes like it
would be with the tyranny right yeah it
should be
except that yeah except that the the the
yeah the tyranny is will be just that
that kind of up down like that top-down
you know light that shines down and kind
of puts everything in place and then
when it reaches the things that it
doesn't that it can't absorb it'll just
it'll completely cut them off you know
like it'll kill them it'll burn them off
you know it'll just destroy them whereas
there's something about Christianity or
like a traditional hierarchy which is a
stretching out in so so you could
imagine right let's say in terms of all
of Christianity it isn't
I think there really there is there's
like a place let's say for it's at least
in in the world there's a plate until
the Last Judgement let's say until the
Last Judgement there's a place for that
buffer to be there and to be slowly
assimilated right and so so it's not it
doesn't it doesn't totally shut itself
off there's a there's a there's a
there's room there's a gate you know
like you said and there's always people
that can come through the gate and that
are always kind of entering and slowly
being signified assimilated but not just
assimilated but also transforming it yes
what it's going to be into what it's
going to become but it's a but it's not
it's not a radical process it's like
this organic transformation let's say
well that's a huge part of what we're
arguing about right now in a culture
which is how is it that you handle the
integration let's say and the answer
isn't no integration no because what
that does is rigidify the structure yeah
because if you if you close it off
completely you also rigidify it inside
yeah and so what that means is the chaos
is gonna break forth inside so cuz you
can't get rid of the chaos now now you
know one of the things we talked about
so it's out for example with the idea of
gay marriage so now there's the excluded
are included and then the question is
well what what is then the
responsibility of the included and the
responsibility of the included is to not
break the structure of the system that
included them yeah you know that's a
really that's a really good way of
seeing that because that's and that's
actually probably the best way of
understanding understanding it in terms
of how it works itself out in real life
it's like you know if you come in if you
come in as you know an assimilated
margin you know as as a margin wants to
participate in in a country or in an
identity or in a group or whatever it is
like in a club like your responsibility
is like you said is to not break what
makes that something thank you you know
if you want to if you want to be you
know if you want to join a I know a
baseball group and you in a baseball
team and you come into the team and
you're the newbie on the team and you
and you all of a sudden expect everybody
to to play basket to play basketball
it's like well then why like what would
it doesn't you know you're going to
destroy the class I can't destroy the
club itself exactly no do you think
that's a victorious simple way yes well
we talked about that a little bit with
the abrahamic stories if I remember
correctly because there was the problem
in the Abrahamic stories of how to deal
with the marginal and so I can't
unfortunately I can't recreate that
on-the-fly husband Pat like you it had
to do with hospitality behavior yeah
right so the rule is I show you
hospitality but that's my rule my
obligation but your obligation is not to
do not to make passes at my wife and
disrupt my household yeah right and then
and then a relationship builds with the
stranger and then and then slowly the
stranger you know it becomes a friend
you know and maybe you then maybe the
stranger marries your daughter at some
point right it's like you know there's
that there's like the possibility of
creating a relationship which which will
integrate the two identities together
but it's a gradual process and one which
has to be done you know with mutual
respect and yeah that's right well you
know the proper spirit well I would I
would say that would be the spirit of
the logos because the logos is also the
thing that goes outside boundaries like
so let's say you have person from Group
A here in person from Group B here and
then they decided to communicate both of
them have to go outside their group and
meet in in the junction between the two
groups is a different place and they
have to make peace but they make peace
there under the guise of themselves as
individuals exploratory individuals and
then maybe the groups can integrate as a
consequence of that right and they then
knowing apart and without fighting and
something appears like something will
manifest itself as whatever is is
holding you know the two groups together
the two families are the two people and
so that logos will with the coming
together let's say let's say two
families is a good example you have two
families you know and then they then
people in the two families intermarry
and so there's something that unites
them too
you know and and it's the in the coming
together that that logos will appear and
will hold hold the relationships in that
lace that marriage is a recreation of
that masculine feminine you yeah and
that's that's associated sometimes with
the androgyny of Christ and sometimes
with there's an old idea and I can't
remember where it comes from that that
Adam before Eve was not for Didache
right yeah more androgynous and draw
hydrogenous right and that Christ as the
second Adam recreates that a draw and
drogyny in the proper manner yeah no I
think so I think I think that that
there's a there's some use find it in
some of the church fathers where they'll
say things like just to help you to
understand and understand it they'll say
things that like that God separated Adam
and Eve Adam into two in view of the
fall right in the sense that it wasn't
the fall but it was the idea that it had
to it has to do with the the idea of
living outside the garden let's say and
and and and having then to come back
together and that coming back together
in in terms of sexual union and in terms
of procreation then is becomes a little
microcosm of what was in the garden
let's say right and so and that's why
also you know like you know Adam I
wonder if that's actually I wonder to
what degree that's actually let's say I
wouldn't say neurophysiological II true
but I'm gonna say something like that
because it seems to me and I made
allegiance to this when we did that talk
about logos men people maybe thought
that it wasn't the most appropriate
thing to say but sexual Union produces
this this brief union in paradise yeah I
think if that's the that's the highest
that's the highest point of sexuality
and that's why sexuality is used as an
image for the union of the soul with God
and it's used as an image of the union
of the church with Christ because the
idea that the unit that the union of the
masculine and the feminine is a glimpse
of eternity it's a glimpse of paradise
well and I I'm not sure that's just an
idea yeah I can t think that that's
that's our can it actually happens yeah
yeah I think that it actually happens
yeah I think so yeah and that's why also
I think that in in Christianity the idea
of taking that lightly right it's very
dangerous the idea of uniting yourself
with with all kinds of people he's very
dangerous because you when you unite
yourself with someone you're actually
creating a very powerful spiritual unity
you know and then if you kind of wonder
that and yet shallow then you don't have
your heart yeah you're devaluing it yeah
and it also to rip you apart because you
leave a part of yourself with that other
person and you leave a part of it's like
you leave you're kind of still attached
to someone and you're leaving a part of
your soul whatever with that person and
they ripped apart so you had what makes
your sin that you might say it makes you
cynical yeah which I would say I think
that sleeping with a hundred women would
leave you cynical for sure I don't see
how it wouldn't I don't see how it went
you would yes yes yeah well that's
that's that's the question no I think
that's a very good way of thinking about
that yeah so we would at least leave you
in a position of you know like the
person who only eats caviar let's say
who doesn't understand how precious
things are you know and to not
understand how precious things are as to
devalue them right if you if you if you
well if that's the highest thing that
you're devaluing then you end up like
Cain with Abel like he kills Abel his
highest ideal and then he says the
punishment is more than he can bear so
if you take what actually is the highest
value and devalue it then you're left
without hope yeah yeah yeah no I mean
that's why that's why I mean I don't
know but it's like the people that I've
known in my life who who who who sleep
around a lot they tend to to have a kind
of nihilistic tendency let's say a blase
tendency like to not how well things can
be discarded yeah yeah and and that and
that and that moment of Union let's say
is also pretty much devalued to just
brief pleasure yeah that's the only way
that it's conceptualized you know when
it is the case to that if you look at
early
miscue 'ti in teenagers it's associated
with antisocial behavior hmm yeah it's a
strong predictor or strong correlative
antisocial behavior interesting yeah now
I'm not saying there's a causal
relationship there but I am saying it's
part of the same constellation right
that's quite clear hmm so yeah all right
well that's probably enough of that yeah
yeah okay okay well that was good man I
I was thinking about these things when I
woke up this morning you know like for
about an hour I mean they were just
flash like crazy yeah you've got that
excited look on you I can I can tend to
discern it now yeah well it's too much
you know it's too much this sort of
thing really is just so it's like Christ
I'd like to get up in the morning and
think about raking the backyard or
something like that yeah so oh well that
was really good Jonathan you think that
you think that way no you think that's
good like you think that we got to what
we wanted we have ya know if you if you
want like think about it I mean I mean
because we had a whole bunch of things
that we said we wanted to talk about
yeah I mean maybe we could we could make
it like whatever every two months or
every month or something well I'm sure
that I'll have the way my mind is
working right now I'm sure that I'll
have some ideas that you you'll be the
right person to talk to about so yeah
well like I said I'm here's see you're
one of these weird intersectional people
a you're a Greek Orthodox wrote French
Canadian icon Carla knows a lot about
post-modernism it's like I think there's
probably exactly one of you in the world
fitty sure I'm sure that's why I think
that is why like I've always been a
marginal person that's why I understand
it so well but I think that the key the
key to my situation right now is that I
I kind of saw it but now I also see how
it can serve the the center let's say
and so that's my job in life I think
that's pretty much I think what I'm
supposed to be right well that's a good
way of ending because the postmodern
claim the postmodern er
his claim is that the center should
serve the margin now but the
counterclaim is the margin should serve
the center now and both those claims are
right yeah and that's also related with
that idea that you already described of
of the image of Christ as the perfect
man saturating the entire hierarchy yeah
no I agree and the first would be the
last and the last will be the first
there's something about that in
Christianity which is absolutely true
that there that there's even something
at there's even something weird that
happens at the end or at the bottom
where there's a mere reflection between
the bottom and the top where like the
lowest thing would be the fool for
example and the highest thing would be
the the holy fool and so there is this
strange completion that happens in the
in the whole thing but it's really a
very it becomes very mystical at that
point it's hard to describe in in
straight categories but well I think
Marlowe's kind of an example of that
well I'm asking myself been asking
myself that for months you know I did
that interview with with dr. Rachel
Fulton Browne about Yad Milo yeah and by
the way she really like would like to
talk to you anyways so that the thing
I'm wondering about him is that in the
in the holy fool usually there's a lot
of self-depreciation and so st. Francis
you know he would go out into the public
space and strip naked you know and he
would he would pass for for a beggar and
all those things and so I think that
that might be a requirement for the Holy
fool is is that the the the humor is not
only against the people around them but
also it turns back on themselves
constantly and so that's what makes them
the holy fool is that is that you can't
criticize them because as as much as
they're criticizing the rulers they're
the structure of the order it turns back
on them and then they act as the lowest
of the low so there's that's what is is
is able to hold them to to hold them in
that high place so something to think
about okay all right all right well I'm
gonna cut the front of this off maybe a
little bit yeah that's my post-it so all
right cool all right good luck with
everything
yeah I've got another lecture tonight oh
that the end of Jacob's Ladder yeah yeah
so now I have to go prepare that
so wait let me let me think about
Jacob's Ladder two seconds did you ever
watch that talk on on on Moses and the
ascent of my talk I'd gave on the on uh
on uh it's called the life of Moses like
st. Gregory st. Gregory of Nyssa on the
life of Moses you should watch that if
you if you have time you should what
it's like it's like 45 minutes and it's
really about the ascent of the mountain
and you sent up the holy ladder mhm
would you email that to me yeah I'll
send you something I'm completely out of
brain house and I'll send you the link
right now I think I think that might be
helpful for you for your talk tonight
can get some rest okay see ya all right
bye-bye